A Finding Aid to the Diane Spodarek papers, 1971-1990, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Diane Spodarek papers
1971-1990
Archives of American Art
Spodarek, Diane
AAA.spoddian
Archival Resource Key
3.6 Linear feet
The papers of artist, editor, and musician Diane Spodarek measure 3.6 linear feet and date from 1971 to 1990. The papers primarily document Spodarek's involvement with the publication Detroit Artists Monthly through administrative files, financial records, artist files, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, sound recordings of performances, printed material, and photographic material.
Biographical / Historical
Diane Spodarek is a multimedia artist, poet, curator, musician, and editor from Detroit, Michigan and New York, New York. Along with Randy Delbake, Spodarek was the founder of Detroit Artists Monthly, a not-for profit arts publication, supported in part by the Michigan Foundation for the Arts, Michigan Council for the Arts, and the National Endowment for the Arts. In the 1970s Spodarek projected her persona "Dangerous Diane" in musical performances before moving to New York City.
Scope and Contents
The papers of artist, editor, and musician Diane Spodarek measure 3.6 linear feet and date from 1971 to 1990. The papers primarily document Spodarek's involvement with the publication Detroit Artists Monthly through administrative files, financial records, artist files, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, sound recordings of performances, printed material, and photographic material.
Administrative files consist of some correspondence, articles of incorporation, certificates of good standing, copyright documentation, manuscripts for articles, and material related to the first Michigan Congress on the Arts. Also included are some "Dangerous Diane" vinyl records featuring Spodarek.
Financial records consist of a budget notebook, tax exemption documents, NEA Organization Grant records, and other grant material.
Artists files for artists including Brian Buczak, Jim Pallas, Tom Sherman, and Lucinda Devlin, consist of resumes, printed material, correspondence, and some photographs of artists featured in Detroit Artists Monthly.
Interview files consist primarily of sound recordings of interviews, interview transcripts, some correspondence, and printed material related to artists and performers used in monthly issues of Detroit Artists Monthly.
Printed material consists of press releases for gallery exhibitions featured in Detroit Artists Monthly, "Dangerous Diane" posters and flyers, and publication proofs for some issues of Detroit Artists Monthly.
Photographic material consists of photographs and slides of artwork, performances, and artists and individuals associated with Detroit Artists Monthly.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 1978 and 2023 by Diane Spodarek.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into six series.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1976-1990 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Financial Records, 1976-1990 (0.1 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Artist Files, 1976-1987 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Interview Files, 1971-1987 (2.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-6)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1976-1979 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 6: Photographic Material, 1977-1978 (0.1 linear feet; Box 2)
Sound recordings; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Artists -- Michigan -- Detroit; Editors -- New York (State) -- New York; Editors -- Michigan -- Detroit; Musicians -- New York (State) -- New York; Musicians -- Michigan -- Detroit; Interviews; Detroit Artists Monthly (1976-1978)
- Administrative Files, 1976-1990; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Administrative files consist of some correspondence, articles of incorporation, certificates of good standing, copyright documentation, manuscripts for articles, and material related to the first Michigan Congress on the Arts. Also included are some "Dangerous Diane" vinyl records featuring Spodarek
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advertising, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alternative Space, 1977-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1977, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Archives of American Art, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Articles Manuscript, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Good Standing, 1977, 1986-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Copyrights, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Dangerous Diane, Conceptually Dangerous", 1979; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound discs (vinyl) (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 1-2)
    There are two copies of the record.
  - "Dangerous Diane and the Dinettes with Duh Detroit Band", 1978; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound discs (vinyl) (Box 1, Folder 9, Item 3-5)
    There are three copies of the record.
  - Exhibition Advertisements, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Michigan Congress on the Arts, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
- Financial Records, 1976-1990; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Series consists of a budget notebook, tax exemption documents, NEA Organization Grant records, and other grant material.
  - Budget Notebook, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Grants, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - NEA Organization Grant, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Tax Exempt Documents, 1976-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Artist Files, 1976-1987; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Artists files for artists including Brian Buczak, Jim Pallas, Tom Sherman, and Lucinda Devlin, consist of resumes, printed material, correspondence, and some photographs of artists featured in Detroit Artists Monthly.
  - David Anderson, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brian Buczak, 1976-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Jim Pallas, 1983-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Tom Sherman, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lucinda Devlin & John Orentlicher, 1976-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
- Interview Files, 1971-1987; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 2.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-6
  Interview files consist primarily of sound recordings of interviews, interview transcripts, some correspondence, and printed material for artists and performers that were used in monthly issues of the Detroit Artists Monthly. Not every file contains a sound recording; some files contain only an interview transcript. Individuals interviewed include Al Herbert, Ray Johnson, Vito Acconci, John Orentlicher, Ken Friedman, Judy Rifka, Marcia Tucker, and Andy Warhol.
  - Untitled Cassette, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 1)
    Writing on cassette is faded and hard to make out.
  - Interview With Photographer, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 2)
  - [??] Donald, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 3)
    first name is illegible
  - Peter Frank, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 6-7)
  - Harst, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 11)
  - Koslelutz, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 12)
    Cassette says 1 of 2. Unclear whether this refers to the interview being on both sides of the cassette or spanning two cassettes. There is only one cassette in the collection.
  - David Philip, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 13-14)
  - Donald Morris, 1976 December 11; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 18)
  - Allie McGhee, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Helen Cheney, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Nancy Gordon, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - John Neff, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Timothy Van Laar, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Betsy Hansell, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Al Herbert, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mike Bobo, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ted Fraser, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dave Jordano, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - James Gilbert, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Robert Pincus-Witten, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Robert Pincus-Witten, 1976, December 7-9; Archival Resource Key; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 1-3)
  - Ian Lyons, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Pam Kladzyk, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Vito Acconci, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Vito Acconci, 1977 January 12; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 4-5)
  - Gallery Attractions, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Imagery "Five Realities" Exhibition Artist Interviews, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Lucinda Devlin, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Robert Broner, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lynn Crimando & Judd Sheldon, Nonce Theatre Company, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Nonce Dance, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 4)
  - Louise Nobili, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jim Hart, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jim Hart, 1977 February; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 6)
  - Gary Smith, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Carol Halstead, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mikki Capparelli, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - John Hegarty, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Edward Ruscha, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Edward Ruscha, 1977 February 24; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Tom Halstead, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Joel Shapiro, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Joel Shapiro, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 15)
  - Edward Weiss, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Weiss, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 17)
  - Deanna Sperka, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - John Baldessari, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - John Baldessari, 1977 April 14; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 8-9)
  - Denise Szykula, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - John Orentlicher, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - John Orentlicher, 1977 June 20; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 12-13)
  - Storm Dettirsch, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Storm Dettirsch, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 5)
  - John Egner, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John Egner, 1977 September 2; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 15)
  - James E. Stout, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jim Stout, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Item 16)
  - James Chatelain, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - J. Chatelain, 1977 August 31; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 14)
  - Dana Atchley, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dana Atchley, 1977 May 3; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 10)
  - Dennis Guastella, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Dennis Guastella, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Karen Roth, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Michael Hall, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Michael Hall, 1977 September 27; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 16)
  - Marcia Tucker, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Marcia Tucker, 1977 September 23; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 4, Item 17-18)
  - Charles McGee, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Charles McGee, 1977 September 29; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 1)
  - Jackson Prison, 1977 June 10; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Item 11)
  - Ken Friedman, 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Ken Friedman, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 3, Item 8-9)
  - Ray Johnson, 1971-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30-33)
  - Ray Johnson, 1977 September 29; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 2)
  - M. J. Bighe, 1977; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 4)
  - John Neff, 1977 November 7; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 5)
  - Stan Dolego, 1977 November 9; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Ivy Sky Rutzky, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Ivy Sky Rutzky, 1977 December 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 7)
  - Andy Warhol and Brigid Polk, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Andy Warhol and Brigid Polk, 1978 January 26; Archival Resource Key; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Item 8-11)
    Cassettes 3 and 4 may be a duplicate interview.
  - Tommy Mew, 1978 January 25; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 12)
  - Dick Higgins, 1978 January 26; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Item 13-14)
  - Germaine Keller, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Germaine Keller, 1978 January 27; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 5, Item 15-16)
  - Stephen Goodfellow, 1978 March 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 17)
  - Dione Carr, 1978 February 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 18)
  - Robert Pincus-Witten, 1978 March 17; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Judy Rifka, 1978 March 14; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Item 2-3)
  - Untitled Interview, 1978 March; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 4)
    Name on cassette is illegible.
  - Jim Rutkowski, 1978 April 12; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 5)
  - Philip Pearlstein, 1978 April 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 6)
  - Keith Aohi, 1978 May 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 7)
  - Al Schmidt, 1978 May 24; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 8)
  - Lynn Blumenthal, 1978 May 29; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 9)
  - Michelle Donor, 1978 June; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 10)
  - Lynn Farnsworth, 1978 July; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 11)
  - Roy Slade, 1978 September 6; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 12)
  - Clause Rinke, 1978 November 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 13)
  - Jay Yager, 1978 November 24; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Item 14-15)
  - Doug Huebler, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Dennis Oppenheim, 1978 December 12; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 5, Item 3)
    Case is labeled, "Ray Johnson 9-29-77"
  - Dennis Oppenheim, 1978 December 12; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 6, Item 16-17)
  - Stephen Goodfellow, 1987 March 20; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 6, Item 18)
  - Cacioppo, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Printed Material, 1976-1979; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material consists of press releases for gallery exhibitions featured in Detroit Artists Monthly, "Dangerous Diane" posters and flyers, and publication proofs for some issues of Detroit Artists Monthly.
  - "Dangerous Diane" Flyers and Posters, circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Press Releases for Gallery Exhibitions, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Publication Proofs, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Photographic Material, 1977-1978; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographic material consists of photographs and slides of artwork, performances, and artists and individuals associated with Detroit Artists Monthly.
  - Art Space, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Artwork, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Slides, Performances, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)